[Music]
do
hello good evening good day everybody
i hope you are all doing very well and
welcome to the newest episode the 83rd
episode 83rd live episode of oscar
widget
uh
so let's see who all is there let me
greet everybody i can see ramesh
shankajeet sorajit cheri
2.0 komal legend anurag
kiran chitra
chuching shorya
kai the persian
brothers don jitega
fire gamer prakar sharma
anshika abhishek
and everybody else good evening and good
day to all of you i hope you're doing
very well
so before we begin before we go into the
q a uh let me just
i hope you're all enjoying the
the podcast that i'm putting up the
conversations that i'm putting up on the
channel
uh i hope you're all getting some value
from it and it's going to keep on coming
and uh
if you're wondering in case you're
wondering who uh who i'm going to invite
next well i would say prepare to be
surprised because i'm gonna go i'm gonna
call people that you may not really
expect or maybe you may not even know
but i'm gonna call people who are
interesting and who have something
interesting to
some interesting perspectives knowledge
etc to share
so it's going to keep on coming at least
two podcast per week right
so with that said let us get into the q
a for today
uh the first question for today is by
arjun
so arjun says we at tamil nadu are
taught we are taught wow we are taught
that tamil nadu was part of a continent
called the kumari condom
a huge land mass that's now submerged
most of our tamil scriptures allege you
the same i would like to i would love to
know your take about this
okay so see
what is my take about this see i am not
an expert in tamil history uh i am aware
of the fact that there are these claims
that there was this
land mass called kumari kandam that is
now submerged there is a story
now the question is how large was this
landmass etc but it said that it was a
huge continent it went all the way god
knows where
so
my perspective is purely scientific if
there is a claim there should be
evidence for it so if some land mass has
been submerged over time for whatever
reason geological reasons tectonic
reasons whatever seismic reasons
then there will be evidence of that
under the sea clearly that should be for
instance we say that there was dwarka
the city of dwarka where we have found
it under the sea that's why i say it
exists right because we have found
actual evidence of it physical evidence
so now this land mass that they claim uh
exists there should be some evidence of
that so let's take a look at um
at a map of the
indian ocean the undersea
region part of the indian ocean let me
remove this and let me share the map
okay look into this so this here
is the map of the ocean floor
and if you look here this here is the
indian subcontinent
this is africa here we have madagascar
and you can actually see
the lines left by the shapes left by by
the uh
movement of the indian subcontinent
continent from africa all the way into
the eurasian land mass
now if we expand this
uh
you can see the continental shelf
which you can see is much higher than
the ocean floor you can see under sea
mountains and so on you can see where
the maldives are the lakshadweep
islands are and so on these are actually
the tops of undersea mountains and so on
so this here is tamil nadu now show me
is there any submerged land mass
continent-sized or even island-sized
land mass
whether on the eastern coast of the
indian subcontinent or the western coast
of indian subcontinent we don't see any
of that
so from the evidence from the hard
geological evidence from the evidence of
what is under the sea uh under the
surface of the ocean we see that there
is no such submerged land mass and all
of these processes these geological
processes etc they occur over millions
of years which far predates
human history so if something was there
in the past two three thousand years
five thousand years it would certainly
be visible here and unfortunately no
such land mass
is visible
and therefore i have to say that uh
either the the
the claim that is made in whatever
literature exists maybe it was about
some small land mass but that has been
uh over time exaggerated into a
continent size something
or either it simply did not exist that's
all i can say i have just shown you the
geological evidence the evidence of what
lies under the surface of the ocean so
clearly there is no
no such thing right
so that is just not that's not my
opinion it's just facts it's just what
lies under the ocean it's very clear
right
so that is
that's just what it is
okay next question
was chess invented in india
that's uh what rohan asks
so uh was j so yes obviously uh
we have to once again look at evidence
so let us look for evidence of ancient
indian chess
let me share that with
you uh one second
so let us simply look for let's do a
google search for indus valley chess
because they call it the indus valley
region right
so if you look here
you will find all of this evidence of
chess boards chess pieces from
mohenjo-daro this here is this this
chess board and these chess pieces i
think they are
presently in present-day pakistan
and you can see that you you clearly
have a great game with the checkered
board checkered pattern
and various pieces which exactly
resembles chess so clearly
this is ancient chess that was played in
ancient india
and so that it that's what it is this
must be at least 5000 years old or
something so this is
undeniable evidence of the fact that
chess was invented in ancient india i
don't know what wikipedia etc say i
don't know what claims they make but
chess is an indian game and it's not
just chess it's it's various other games
as well various other board games uh
snakes and ladders also
is a game that was invented in india
even the game of polo originates in
india in manipur
uh the world's oldest polo ground still
exists it is still functional it's in
the city of impal manipur so all of
these ancient games as you can see are
indian games and you can see there were
horse
figurines etc and so on
so to
answer
to summarize yes
chess was indeed invented in india and
it spread to other other cultures other
civilizations other countries nations
etc
from india
uh so most likely i think chess
spread to the western world from persia
so it came to persia from india
and from persia it went westwards and to
other places even the chinese
i think they
acquired this game why are their
contacts with india
all right uh saurabh says
why
do many historians refer to the rig
vedic people
peoples as tribal populations rather
than a clean clan rather rather than
plants or civilized societies
because these are these
uh the original historians who spoke
about the rig vedic tribes were
europeans they're british
and
from their perspective everything that
is not european is backward and all that
and that's why they called the rigvedic
clans as tribes so what is the
definition of a tribe i've spoken about
this before let me speak again
a tribe is a small
isolated group of people who have not
developed an advanced society
so it's a
a group of people a small society maybe
a hundred people maybe five hundred
maybe thousand two thousand people or
something like that small reasonably
small group of people
who have been isolated for quite some
time who are not in contact with other
cultures with the other groups of
individuals other societies etc who are
not in touch with them who are isolated
and whose culture whose
way of life is not very advanced that is
the definition of a tribe
right
so one of the hallmark of a tribe is
that it doesn't have an advanced culture
and it's nowhere near the status of a
civilization when it comes to the rig
vedic peoples they had a very highly
advanced culture they were a
civilization a proper civilization not
just a small culture
they had
incredible literature
they had their own histories of what
came
along a long time before them as well
the puranas and all that
they had records of the past and so on
so they were a very highly advanced
society they were a civilization and
these so-called tribal groups what are
alleged to be tribal groups are actually
clans extended families extended
families uh
extended lineages
so that's what the rig vedic people were
they were they were clans they were
groups
of extended families
right so that's what they were and the
problem is that today's historians see
the 20th century historians and even the
21st century historians they blindly
slavishly copy the language that was
introduced by the british colonial
writers and that's why you see even
today in the phd thesis and whatever
literature comes out in the academic
domain
they still refer to the rig vedic
peoples as tribal groups
it's just blind adherence to
colonial tradition
and that tells you this that tells you
about the state of indian academia it's
it's uh it's abysmal unfortunately
so that in short is why
this notion
still persists and this nomenclature is
still continuing today
dungar singh chauhan says why is russia
so much inclined towards china can we
see a second cold war in the coming
future considering the tension between
russia and nato
the second cold war is already here we
are in the middle of the second cold war
right so why is russia inclined towards
china see first of all
uh the west is very much anti-russia
they see russia as a big threat because
russia even though it has a small
economy it is not even in the top 10
economies in the world but still and yet
it has a very powerful military a really
powerful military that can actually uh
pose a significant
clear and present threat to europe to
nato
and russia also has the world's largest
nuclear arsenal right so russia is
a very significant uh military power one
of the top three military powers in the
world for sure
so that's why the west
essentially when we talk about the west
when we talk about nato we're talking
about the us
the us is the only superpower in the
world right now china is not a
superpower all right china is an
aspiring superpower they want to become
a superpower so the us is the only
superpower in the world and they see any
other large power any other big power is
a threat
they don't want to have any other big
powers in the world
and therefore they are so much anti
russia they have essentially encircled
russia via
nato etc and they are constantly
threatening russia and uh
taking various actions to undermine the
the
long-term national interest of russia
and therefore russia and the same thing
goes with china china is an emerging
power it is an aspiring superpower the
americans feel greatly threatened with
good reason by china and therefore it is
natural for these two countries who are
both uh
opposing the us who are both being
actively opposed by the us it is natural
for these two countries to converge
together because
at the moment in the present time and
even in the foreseeable future their
national interests align their national
interests converge and therefore russia
is uh in a variety of ways you could say
uh cooperating with china
so i had a guest a few days ago called
who willing
who calls this
cooperation with the systemic
cooperation between russia and china she
has given it the term dragon bear right
so this is a phenomenon that we are
observing
so russia doesn't have a very large
economy but it is a very powerful
military the chinese can help russia in
a variety of ways and the russians can
can act as a mercenary force for the
chinese wherever required so it's it's a
good match
right now geopolitically long term
if you look at the long term the next 20
30 years that kind of horizon in that
case you will see them as geopolitical
adversaries but right now there is a
great deal of cooperation with between
them
so that is the reason why russia is
inclined towards china because it suits
them right it is what works best for
them in the
short to medium term at least from the
perspective of their shared
interests
so uh that's why russia is inclined
towards china and we are already in the
middle of a second cold war we are
seeing a complete bipolarization of the
world so that is
and you can see that there are lots of
tensions there is this uh trade war
going on between the us and the chinese
and all kinds of disagreements
the chinese are saber rattling and all
that so yes this is already a cold war
we are already in the middle of a cold
war
balram says oh
thank you for the episode with anujar
i'm glad you liked it
what if china and russia rule the world
instead of the u.s how different would
it be
like human rights freedom of speech etc
you know human rights freedom of speech
these are nice concepts nice ideas
uh we are supposed to believe that the
western form of of uh democracy is a
liberal democracy where freedom of
speech is guaranteed it is absolute but
look around look around you and see
what's happening
can you see the assault on joe rogan
they're trying to cancel him they're
trying to de-platform him
uh various very powerful political
figures like barack obama etc are armed
twisting spotify
into
they're trying to force spotify to d
platform joe rogan and there there's so
much censorship going on in various
domains and various platforms etc so
free speech freedom of speech doesn't
exist even in the west
and if you talk about human rights come
on look at what what's happening
uh
all the vaccine mandates
uh what's happening in canada right now
what's happening in australia
and and the abysmal track record of nato
and other countries western countries
when it comes to bombarding civilians
with no regard for human rights for the
for the lives of civilians women
children etc there's no such concept the
human rights is only a nice stick to
beat certain countries with when it
suits them
so uh
so all of these concepts are just
illusory
right
if you look at the kind of sanctions
they have imposed on various countries
it's it's causing starvations and
starvation and deaths
uh from various uh reasons
if you look at what the west is doing
indirectly in yemen it's it's uh
it's it's it's terrible it's a human
humanitarian crisis they've created so
there is no such thing as human rights
and freedom of speech and all that it's
just
highfaluting values that they talk about
when it's convenient
for them right
so if russia and china rule the world
it's going to be much of the same
they may not
uh
put up this pretense of believing in
human rights and freedom of speech and
all that
the western world simply pretends to
believe in these things and yet they do
whatever they want to do whenever it
suits them so it's you know power is
just power
right now the power the overall power
the balance of power it lies with the
west with the united states in the
future it may not be so but
the world will not really change a lot
after all power needs order it won't it
needs an orderly world and when you want
order you need rules and stability so
the world will go on the way it is
whether it's one
party that rules the world one one power
or or another power and china and russia
will not rule the world together if that
ever happens
uh there's no place in in
for two
powers in in such a system there's all
this there can only be one power or two
opposing
and balanced powers
so in case the u.s falters and and
uh and it declines as a global power
then they you will see the emergence of
competition and
and an adversary relationship emerging
between russia and china themselves they
will not rule together impossible it
simply doesn't work that way
so that's what i can say about this
okay re attacks says do you think the
monetization worked for india
so what was the stated aim of
demonetization the stated aim of
demonetization was to
do away with black money reduce
corruption and all that
so
there's been a lot of commentary about
this and lots of people allege that
demonetization never worked etc but let
me give you a different perspective
uh i think demonetization happened in
2017 or something most likely 2017
now the world is not the world india
has changed a lot since then and think
about how india has changed today
in in 2017 or whichever year
demonetization happened
india's informal economy was more than
50 of the overall economy it was
something like 55 or 60 percent of the
indian economy the informal economy
which was which was uh not taxed it was
essentially all black money
right all the transactions that happened
by cash cannot be traced there can be no
record of this transaction and therefore
those are not taxed and that's why it's
all black money
right that's the informal economy
in today's india in in the india of 2022
i think about 10 to 15 of the economy is
informal everything else is formal
because of the rise in online
transactions because of the
decline in reliance on cash
if you go if you are in any indian city
or town today you can go and buy
vegetables and fruits and small
groceries with your phone you don't need
to carry cash anymore
right and the other thing which has
happened is the gst which has
essentially unified the entire country
under one tax umbrella for the first
time since 1947.
so all of this is essentially a
consequence of demonetization the
formalization of the economy is an
enormous step in reducing corruption
right
today you most of the transactions are
done online
electronically
and that is one of the best ways of
eliminating corruption
and i think it's going to go further in
the coming years
most likely in the next 10 years almost
everything will become formal and cash
may be a thing of the past so that
itself is an enormous blow against
corruption whether we realize it or not
right
so i think demonetization maybe this
stated something
but the actual overall effect has been
that of formalizing the economy
and
making the economy making
making it easier for small businesses to
to
transact
their business
and all that so i think it was a very
good move
uh they may have uh the the prime
minister may have said one thing but
if you look at the bigger picture it has
it's actually worked i think it was a
very good move because it was the first
step that led to the
formalization
of the economy in just five years so
it's it's a very rapid change actually
if you look at it that way because
if you want to see change in a nation
you have to look at it decade by decade
but over here we are seeing it we are
seeing it in a period of just four to
five years so that's a very rapid change
that's happened and demonetization was
the first step it was the catalyst
that triggered of this big change so i
think it was a great move it's really
worked
okay this is my diya i've been asking
the same question for months
in both comments and live chat it's
difficult to get under attention yes i
know there are thousands of comments
coming in every day so yeah anyway i got
i go i found the comment so the question
is do you find do you think the universe
is finely tuned and created by a supreme
power which coded how everything should
work time laws of physics dna evolution
etc or all of this accidentally happened
if the universally accidentally came
into existence then our life is also
accidental with it without any so-called
spiritual intention or purpose right
i mean how many questions do you have
the uh uh
do you think humans can get superpowers
by advanced meditation do you think
himalayan yogis have really superpowers
and all that is it just myths let me
take the question about the fine tuning
so there is this theory
uh that the universe is fine-tuned for
life that our universe is fine-tuned and
it is no accident
so if you look at the various constants
of nature
there are a bunch of constants in nature
which do whose origin we don't know but
if you change the values of these
constants like the fine structure
constant the the strength of the
gravitational force and so on
or the strength of the electromagnetic
interaction just some some examples i'm
giving
there are a lot more of those
right the the strength of the strong
interaction weak interaction
and so on so if you change any of these
parameters if you tweak them just a
little bit then the universe becomes
impos
the kind of life that we have on this
planet becomes impossible
and therefore
some people claim
that the universe is fine tuned for life
i think it's a silly argument first of
all it's not a physical argument it's a
philosophical argument it's pure
speculation right
so so
imagine that you could create a number
of universes all with a different uh
kind of different values of the
different of the various parameters then
you will you would come up with
different uh
strengths of interaction and in
different ways
so so the laws of nature the laws of
physics would behave differently each in
each universe
to a small degree
and i think in such a case if you had
if you had a million different universes
with slightly different a small slightly
with with different variations of these
parameters then i think that you would
find life of different kinds
emerging
in these various universes the only
example of life that we have is the one
is what we see on our planet and
therefore we have only one data point
you cannot build an entire theory from
one data point
so this is just pure speculation i don't
think our universe is
special somehow
i think if you had the different values
of these parameters or different kind of
tuning then different kinds of life
would emerge right but life i'm sure
would have emerged in some form of or
the other
so i do not buy into this argument of
fine tuning
and now when you ask about supreme
powers and all we have no evidence of
the supreme powers from the perspective
of spirituality philosophy etc that's a
whole different perspective i am
answering as a physicist i'm answering
from the perspective of science and
physics from the perspective of science
and physics we have no evidence of a
supreme power
so it's all about belief right and
belief has no place in science science
is all about observations
measurements
and what's observable and measurable
that's all it is and therefore you know
all of this uh
it's possible that somebody is coding
the universe there's a programmer
there's a great programmer somewhere out
there who has coded the universe so
you're talking about this this
simulation hypothesis now
it's possible
what do i think is it fine is it created
by superimpower or is it accidentally
happened or whatever i don't know
i don't know how do i answer these
questions i don't have sufficient data
to answer this question so this is one
of the big mysteries in life uh people
some people choose to believe
theory a or theory b or believe in one
god or multiple gods our
culture our civilizational uh
literary texts etc i have a very clear i
have a very clear
uh
understanding
of how the universe came to be
in in hinduism what we call hinduism
there is the concept of the multiverse
for sure
but
from a scientific perspective we don't
have evidence of that i'm not saying it
it means it doesn't exist it may not be
true but we don't have evidence that's
all i'm saying
so that's what i can say that i don't
have an idea i don't have evidence for
either this way or that way so i can't
say i all i can say
honestly
is i don't know
right
do you think humans can get uh super
powers by advanced meditation etc
superpowers
those are not superpowers
people talk about uh being able to
utilize 100 of the of your brain etc
that's what meditation does i'm not sure
if you can utilize what they call 100 of
the brain but you can certainly
increase your focus to a significant
degree by several orders of magnitude
if you
uh practice meditation consistently for
several years like these yogis do and
that's that's what gives them certain
powers that ordinary human beings would
not have but these are not super powers
or spiritual powers or magical powers
these are physical powers
right
limit in brief do you think nuclear
energy
is the best source of energy
in brief if i were to explain
chandrasekhar's limit it is
the maximum possible mass of a stable
white dwarf what is a white dwarf it is
essentially what what is left behind
when a star like our sun eventually uh
reaches the end of its
life so to say the end of its life as a
as a functional
star so it is no longer a star it's a
white white dwarf so our sun is a
it's it's a
it's a medium-sized star i think it's a
yellow dwarf i don't know what the exact
categorization is
but after about five million years or so
from today five billion years sorry not
million billion
about around that time the sun will
become a red super giant and then it
will just
its outer layers will just dissipate
away and what will be left of it will be
the core
which will essentially be the size of
maybe a city
a metropolis or so but it will have more
or less the mass of an entire star
inside it so it's an extremely dense
compact
uh
stellar form which is uh
which
is not a black hole but it's very dense
it is it is held it is what prevents its
collapse into a black hole is
electron degeneracy pressure
and so what is the maximum size that a
white dwarf can have it is uh the
chandrasekhar limit which can be
calculated
and the calculation is available online
so it's it is currently believed to be
about 1.44
solar masses so if a star is larger than
that
then it will collapse into either a
neutron star
or a black hole so if a star is more
massive than 1.44 solar masses roughly
then it will collapse into either a
neutron star or even further into a
black hole so that is chandra the
chandrasekhar limit
do i think nuclear energy is the best
source of energy it's one of the
cleanest and best sources of energy as
long as you
design your reactors properly and you
operate them properly so um
so yeah it is
a very clean source of energy especially
if we are able to in the future
hopefully
uh
uh design fusion reactor so there are
two kinds of nuclear reactions
fission and fusion
fission is when a heavy nucleus such as
uranium two three two three five two
three eight whichever whichever it is or
plutonium or even thorium when one of
these heavy nuclei
breaks up
splits due to radioactivity you can
induce the the fission and it and it
releases a large amount of energy and
you can create a chain reaction if it is
a runaway chain reaction it's a nuclear
explosion a nuclear bomb if you can
control the reaction with the cadmium
rods or whatever
inside the reactor then you can harness
that energy and that's what a nuclear
reactor does so that is fission there's
a there's another more energetic nuclear
reaction which is nuclear fusion
so so far we have not been able to
achieve controlled fusion we have been
able to achieve uncontrolled fusion
reactions which are essentially
thermonuclear bombs
that's a fission fusion bomb it's a
fusion reaction triggered by an initial
fission explosion
so that's a fission fusion thermonuclear
bomb but that is an uncontrolled
reaction
but we still haven't been able to
achieve a controlled sustained fusion
reaction that's what various countries
are trying the europeans are trying the
chinese are trying it and so on india is
doing nothing of course
so that is nuclear
fusion
so that is an even better form of energy
in when we are when we have a fission
reaction going a fission reactor nuclear
reactor you have these by-products which
is called nuclear waste which is
extremely
not good for the environment so it has
to be confined somewhere you know sealed
properly and
and uh
it's buried deep underground and all
that you know for all posterity or
something like that
but in when you if you are if you are
able to
build a fusion reactor there will be
almost no by-product at all so it's way
cleaner than a fission reaction
so i think that nuclear energy is
i would consider it to be green energy
of
and and a future fusion reactor would be
even better so yeah that's what i can
say about nuclear energy
yeah this is what we had okay next
kai the person says iran's economy has
been crippled
will the islamic regime fall anytime
soon khamenei is very old and there are
many protests across the country
and they want shah pahlavi's son to come
back
um
yes iran's economy has been crippled
there is there are these sanctions that
the west has imposed the u.s has imposed
these sanctions and it's been going on
for a very long time
ever since the uh revolution of 1979
which was a very
anti-american reaction of sorts you
could say
uh that's there's a long history behind
behind that revolution and why it was
anti-american but the thing is
the americans have imposed sanctions on
iran essentially since that time
so it has crippled iran's economy to a
great extent
there have been lots of
problems in iran uh so the question is
will the islamic regime fall anytime
soon well
iran is currently now
entering into you could say
a partnership or alliance with china the
chinese are going to invest
tens of billions of dollars into iran
obviously at a certain price
so the chinese will prop up iran's
economy and iran's
the the the whatever ruling regime we
have in iran right now you know the
mullahs or whatever the khmer is how
many
uh so you have the the
clerics who are the
who are the overall rulers and then you
have elected presidents and so on who
are
you could say
not very powerful so that's what we have
now you're saying that there are
protests across across the country they
want sharp helleve sun to come back
yeah there are protests against the
country across the country to some
extent we don't show we're not sure
what's actually happening because
all of this information is tightly
controlled and
any news of such protests would be
they would try their best to suppress
such news going out of the country
so there is clearly a certain degree of
disaffection with the regime
the regime has
caused a great deal of suffering because
of their policies geopolitical policies
and the ensuing sanctions and all that
will the islamic regime fall anytime
soon well
that's a whole different story what what
is holding this regime together it is
force it is power that is holding the
regime together they have the control of
the army and whatever other militias you
have the revolutionary guards the basic
guards and all that
so that is the
what gives them the the
power on the streets of the country and
as long as they have that as long as
they're able to control the army and the
militias
then they will not fall
no matter how much people protest
if you have guys with guns
with overwhelming force then none of
these protests
will work
and as long as this regime is supported
by
large powers such as china
it's going to continue as long as it
provides whatever value china seeks
so i think it is it is quite
hard
to see
the islamic regime falling anytime soon
considering the support they are getting
from china right now right
i would say that the only way the regime
would fall if these if the americans
launch a military invasion
which the which
you know who knows they may they may
we don't know
uh maybe it's not really advisable to
have an have a military adventure in
iran when
things when we have other tensions going
on in other parts of the world in
eastern europe in in the straits
in in the
south china sea the champasi and all so
the americans may not do that right now
i mean
do that when i say do that i mean uh
invade iran or
do any military action in iran so i
would say that this the regime
will continue as far as i can see at
least for the short to medium duration
okay venus says can north korea and
south korea unite again as one single
country like germany and vietnam good
question so uh
we had the situation in vietnam in the
60s and 70s
i think it is it's in the 60s right
in the 50s and 60s vietnam was first
under french occupation french
colonialism they kicked the french out
and then you had the division of vietnam
the communists and the anti-communists
the chinese got involved the americans
got involved we had the so-called
vietnam war the vietnamese call it the
american war
and the communists prevailed ho chi minh
prevailed with the help of the support
of the chinese the soviets etc were in
various overt and covered ways
so vietnam was first divided at this
time during this period into north
vietnam and south vietnam the north
vietnamese were the communists the south
vietnamese were the
the ones that the americans supported
and the north vietnamese won and they
reunified the country by force
right
so vietnam was divided
because of external powers they did not
divide because of a civil war and think
it's external powers outside powers that
divided the country it was foreign
interference in their internal affairs
that divided the dream
why did
germany
why was germany divided into east
germany and west germany it's again
because of foreign powers
because of the united states and the
ussr that divided the country it is
these foreign powers that broke the
country into two pieces and that's how
it remained until the dissolution of the
ussr
so it's a 1989 onwards at germany i
think i think it's 1989 that the berlin
wall fell in the country began the
process of reunification
and what triggered that
the um
the breakup
of the ussr
the demise of the ussr is what triggered
that so the americans won the cold war
and that's how germany was reunified on
american terms
right
so again there is external interference
that
that we are seeing in this right
now when it comes to north korea and
south korea the the division of the two
koreas is a consequence of this of the
korean war of the 1950 of the 1950s
55 was it look it up somewhere around
that time
and again there is foreign interference
in this
uh the chinese versus the americans and
they divided the country essentially
along this uh
ceasefire line which is not the
ceasefire has never been official they
have technically stated still at war but
it is these two countries that divided
uh
korea into north korea and south korea
it was not the koreans who did this
it was the interference of foreign
powers in the in the internal affairs of
korea that caused the division of the
country
and the chinese who were aided by the
soviets at the time they installed a
puppet regime in north korea
the kim dynasty
it was kim il-sung
then kim jong kim
jong-il and then kim jong-un i think
that's the names
apologies if i got the pronunciation
wrong in some way
so that's what it was so again this is
foreign interference so can the two
koreas reunite can they be reunified i
think it can happen it will happen
either if the americans win the tussle
against china or the chinese win the
tussle against the us
or if foreign interference ceases
in that case the country will over over
time
reach its own equilibrium and over time
the two countries will reunify as one
because they're the same people the same
culture
so it will take time but yeah it is all
of these divisions of countries these
partitions so to say are because of
foreign powers meddling in countries and
that's what we saw in india as well
right
so
i hope that answers the question
vishal says gared is the name of a
mythical bird in the mongolian culture
similar to the indian sanskrit word
garuda
it was also the name of chinggis khan's
pet eagle
does that mean that mongolia was in
contact with the indian culture buddhism
hinduism even before the great quran
excellent question
so gared the the mongolian gareth is
garud nothing else it is the guru it is
the indian guru the sanskrit
it is believed to be the name to have
been the name of one of chinggishkhan's
pet eagles you are right that's what i
have read
i'm not sure if that's tested in the
secret history of the mongols or not but
it's certainly what the mongolians
themselves say
so the question is does it mean that
mongolia was in contact with indian
culture even before the time of the
great hagan ching is khan most certainly
it was
see indian uh trade delegations and
cultural emissaries had been going
eastwards
since the time of kanishka the great our
one of our greatest emperors right
and he lived in
somewhere between the first and second
centuries a.d
so uh ching is khan lived in the
13th
century in the 14th century
so
you had the the
presence of these cultural and trade
delegations from india in the eastern
world in china and eastern asia for more
than a thousand years before chinese
khan was even born
and therefore mongolia is north of china
and there would certainly have been
influence of this
indian culture over there as well you
will find
buddhist ruins in mongolia that far
predate the time of qing khan
right so you
we do have archaeological evidence of
buddhist
structures
monuments
uh sculptures carvings in some parts of
mongolia that
far predate chingashkhan and therefore
it is certainly
therefore it is clearly a fact
that mongolia was in contact with indian
culture long before the time of the
great hagan ching is khan and indian
culture see
the way historians portray the spread of
indian culture eastwards is that these
were all buddhist delegations buddhist
culture that was being spread there but
that is a distortion it's a fabrication
if you see the actual scholars who went
eastwards
such as kumara jiva etc they were not
only
well versed in buddhist philosophy but
also in the four vedas
and you will find that hinduism spread
all the way
eastwards to japan you will see hindu
gods and goddesses
worshiped in japan
even today with japanese names today is
the day of saraswati puja today
what is the date today the 5th of
february 2022 today is saraswati puja
day saraswati is worshiped in japan she
is one of the major goddesses in japan
they call her bin zaitin
so she did not come
via air mail into japan
the the spread of indian culture
happened via china via
mongolia and eastern asia into japan
so it's clear that hindu practices made
their way into into japan and today they
are regarded as buddhist gods and
goddesses and deities but these are
clearly hindu gods and goddesses so yes
so what i would say is that
the influence of hinduism buddhism had
been
there in this region for more than a
thousand years before chinese khan was
born and you will see the
evidence of that even today
so to answer your question in brief to
summarize yes mongolia was certainly in
contact with the indian culture long
before the time of the great chinese
khan and after
the
emergence of the yuan dynasty
uh the mongolians adopted the buddh the
the tibetan form of buddhism they uh
there was this
guru-shishi relationship between tibet
and mongolia the tibetans were the gurus
the mongolians were the shishas and they
offered protection to the guru so tibet
became a mongol protectorate mongolia
never occupied tibet but tibet was under
the mongol empire's protection
so that's how events went
kanha but says
why wasn't any persian empire able to
get inside the indian mainland
please take this question and can you
also talk about the assyrian queen
semiramis
so you are right
um
the india persia border has more or less
been fixed for
i would say 3000 years at least
and that is the present-day boundary of
pakistan and persia right and and
gandhara i've got afghanistan and persia
so that is the historical border between
india and persia
now afghanistan
the the region of gandhara has over time
been influenced
by both
to some extent by persia as well today
the afghans
they speak the dhari language which is a
form of persian
and the linguists even consider pashto
to be an ironic language which i do not
agree with at all but that's besides the
point
so uh overall you are right
the persian empire none of the various
kings of the hakshah manish dynasty the
akmir dynasty ever tried to invade india
adarios the king
the rayawas
darya's they call him
he did uh
include
some western regions of present-day
pakistan in his empire so that that has
always been kind kind of diffused the
boundary has the boundaries over time
over the centuries they move here and
there little to some extent so some part
of india
was part of the persian empire under
derivatives but there was never an
invasion
of india a proper invasion of india the
way the persians in kept on invading
to the west
so the persians were militarily
expansionist during the time of the
cabinet dynasty during the time of
kurush which is cyrus uh
which is zexis and so on
and they always
wanted to expand westwards and they came
into conflict with the
greeks on several occasions
like in the middle of the fifth century
before the
during the time of the peloponnesian war
which i have spoken about in other
episodes
so for some reason the persians were not
inclined they did not want
to invade india
they certainly had the military
capabilities or maybe india also had
powerful
armies and so on so maybe there is one
reason or maybe they saw some kind of
cultural affinity which they certainly
had with india when the persians were an
offshoot of the ancient indian
population
one of the i mean
it is the
it is the vedic parshwa tribe
see once again i am also using the wrong
term
i'm using the word tribe here because we
are so ingrained with this word it was
the parshwa clan let me correct myself
it was the parshwa clan
of the vedic people
that went westwards from india westwards
from present-day sindh and balochistan
and settled in what is now called persia
the word persia comes from
the name of the clan the powerful people
so um so yes the persians were
they had indian ancestry their language
the old persian language was essentially
an upper branch dialect of sanskrit
so the same language the same culture
the same ethnicity eventually the
culture changed they became
quasi
it's uh they see they became
zoroastrians
zoroastrianism is not monotheism by any
means it's a polytheistic
uh
religion so to say
so they over time they became different
culturally
but for some reason and we still don't
know the exact reasons why
the persians also never tried to invade
india there was no attempted invasion of
india ever by the persians no serious
attempted invasion of india there may
have been some
small border skirmishes here here or
there but there was never any enmity
between any persian emperor or king and
any indian emperor of king any
significant of any significant kind
that's interesting that's something i
may need to ponder about
so you have asked a very interesting
question
uh the reason why they were not able to
get inside the indian mainland is that
is because they never tried now why did
they never try it
that's a fascinating question
that's something i'm going to spend some
time thinking about
so i i appreciate this question i really
it's a very interesting question a
deeper the deeper question is why didn't
they do it
why did they never try to invade india
and that's something nobody has even
asked or tried to answer the same way
that nobody has in the past 700 years
tried to answer the question of why
chinese can't never
chingaskhan refused to invade india so
the the question now is why did the
persians refuse to ever attempt an
invasion of india that's which is which
is very interesting
uh so the other question is about the
assyrian queens sumerum
see listen i am not very
i don't know a lot about samira miss uh
she lived in the most likely in the
eighth or ninth century bc
uh
my knowledge about this lady this queen
is not very deep
um
she was most likely one of the first
women ever to become an empress or a
queen
in the assyrian
kingdom you know syria
and it is also alleged that she uh tried
to invade india see the syrians are not
persians okay by the way the assyrians
are a different ethnicity a different
culture of different people
uh they were located in present-day uh
what they call west asia iraq that
region
north west of persia
so it is uh it is believed that this
queen she attempted an invasion of india
and she was beaten back by by one of the
indian kings i forget the name
so i think you
uh
maybe you guys if you're interested you
can look it up it's an interesting uh
small chapter of history
uh and she's certainly a significant
historical figure in assyria
for sure
so that's what i can see in brief about
queen semiramis
rama lakshmi says there are two
questions here firstly why didn't the
british give reparations to india
whereas they gave reparations to new
zealand after the withdrawing and
secondly the us wants democracy to be
everywhere even when where it doesn't
require to be
like iraq afghanistan etc then why
doesn't it try to do that with the
saudis
okay let's take the first question why
didn't the british give reparations to
india
see why the question i would like to ask
a counter question why where the british
in india is my counter question
why did the british come to india
why did they spend all these centuries
in india what were they doing in india
what was the purpose of their being here
in india
and why did they leave india so the
answer is very simple they were in india
to loot plunder pillage
and destroy india
the
the objective wasn't destruction the
objective was to extract all of india's
wealth
out of india and siphon it off
to
england
they wanted to enrich themselves at
india's expense in a variety of ways and
that's what they achieved over the
centuries
and finally in 1947 it was no longer
feasible possible for them to stay in
india because of a variety of reasons
and one of the reasons was that
there was nothing more left to take out
of india india had been sucked dry over
the centuries
the uk had become an enormously wealthy
country
just off of
off the back of the wealth that they
stole from india
historians have estimated that this
amounts to approximately
45 trillion dollars in today's money
approximately
so that's like more than the gdp of any
country
right today
annual gdp i mean
so uh that's why the british came to
india then why would they give money
back to india when they left the whole
purpose was to steal money from india
and
why do you give reparations you give
reparations to somebody
because if you don't give reparation
then there will be consequences was
india strong enough to impose
consequences on the british no
even today india is in no position to
armed with the british in giving
reparations so reparations are given
only when there is a significant threat
to your
long-term interests only in that case
for instance the nazis had to give the
german sorry the nazis were defeated in
world war ii and the germans had to give
reparations to the french and two
various other countries because there
was a gun pointed at their heads
right by the americans by the winning
powers that's why they had they were
forced they were obliged they were
obligated to give reparations
there was no such
obligation on the british nobody forced
them nobody
said that they'll do this or else and
that's why they did not give reparations
to india
right very simple
now uh the u.s wants democracy but why
not in saudi arabia see you know what
democracy is just an
the us uses democracy the pretext of
democracy whenever it wants to
effect
a regime change in any country
so they use the protective pretext of
democracy to invade and destroy libya
and they did the same thing with iraq
and they have done the same thing in
various other parts of the world the
saudis are very useful to the u.s the
saudis have been supplying oil to the
u.s for all these decades and even today
the saudis are an important geopolitical
factor in the middle east in west asia
and they are very useful to the u.s they
serve a very a variety of useful
purposes and that's why the americans
will not
will keep their hands off saudi arabia
and of course as you can see today the
saudis are also implementing a variety
of
liberal reforms etc just to stay on the
on the good side
of the
western world especially the u.s so
that's how it goes so democracy the u.s
doesn't want democracy they when they
use the pretext of democracy whenever
they want to
effect regime change somewhere
that's all it is
next question is by ayan chakrabarti how
are the stones of the rama saitu bridge
floating
are they really floating or is there
or is there something more to its
structure
and aren't there any other evidences of
the ramayana other than the ram situ
what about the sea
sigiriya rock fortress let's talk about
the ramsay there are like 15 questions
in here
let me take the major question
how are the stones of the rama bridge
floating well i have never seen a
floating stone i haven't visited the
place but i have seen plenty of
photographs
uh of the structure you can look up
photographs online
on on
google images bing images whatever your
favorite search engine is
and you will not see a single floating
stone there
now i have seen some images on social
media where people claim that there is a
bucket of water and there is a stone
from this place which is floating well
what's the evidence that came from there
if you look at the structure the
large-scale the large-scale structure
between
southern india and and northern sri
lanka
you will see that the structure is
mostly submerged there's nothing
floating there so i don't know on what
basis people make the claim that stones
are floating
and i think that it's written in some
text which one is it is it the ram chair
or something in which they say that the
there was magic and the stones were
floating no you know what
over the over the centuries over
thousands of years stories
get embellished with all kinds of
additional
facts additional additional claims
so you have to look beyond all the
embellishments and try to dig out the
actual factual data and what actually
happened is that the entire bridge was
constructed
uh i'm not sure how it was done
and how long it took but it was an
actual land bridge that was constructed
between india and lanka there was no
floating stones there
it was a superhuman effort and it was
actually done so there is no evidence of
a single floating stone look at the
images go there
look at the photographs look at the
satellite images look at the drone
images look at the aircraft images look
at actual images taken from the beaches
and from the actual structure you will
not see a single floating stone there
i personally haven't seen
any
any evidence of that so that's what i
can say
so is there any other evidence of the
ramayana other than the ram situ well
i'm not sure about that but this one is
there right so we need to examine this
one
and i hope that the asi and the
government of india will take some
interest and do some actual
archaeological work there and see if you
find additional evidence of human
activity
in this
structure
what about the sigria rock fortress it's
it's it's a rock fortress in sri lanka i
am not quite sure if it is connected to
the ramayana or not
but
the
presence of this structure the bridge
between india and sri lanka is
well it says it's the
what else do you need to to prove that
this these events actually happened
uh saurabh says there's an entire
section in the mahabharat about raj
dharma governance
do you think that we indians were the
first to develop the entire system of
governance on a large scale
see we know for a fact that india
is the oldest civilization in the world
that's not that is beyond any dispute
but we also know that india was the
first
large-scale
urban civilization in the world
large-scale urban civilization so if you
look at the sapta sindhu region the
so-called indus valley or harappan phase
of india civilization which is the
saraswati hindu phase of our history
we find that we had a large scale
widespread urban civilization urban
civilization properly well-planned
cities with
with brilliant amenities excellent
drainage systems
excellent engineering hydro engineering
multi-storage buildings excellent
ports harbors
and all that
and this is at least 5000 years before
today
there is no other civilization
civilization like that in the entire
world
right
and the
geographical extent of this civilization
was larger than egypt and mesopotamia
and all these other civilizations put
together even if you add all of these
civilizations together the land area it
is still dwarfed by the land area of the
indian civilization the saraswati
civilization
and it
is clear that you cannot have such a
vast
urban
highly technologically advanced
well-organized
stable civilization
without an
extraordinarily good system of
governance
so there you have evidence
of the fact
that we had
excellent
governance over 5000 years ago now i
don't know when the mahabharata happened
there are all kinds of claims none of
these claims is proven beyond any doubt
but most likely
the mahabharata could have possibly
perhaps
been to some extent
in some way
contemporaneous possibly perhaps
with the saraswati hindu phase of
india's civilization because in the
mahabharata you have
accounts of cities
in the ramayana we don't have large
scale cities there is no mention of
large
metropolitan
cities
so
it is possible that the events of the
mahabharata happened
closer
to the time time scale of the saraswati
hindu phase of india civilization and at
that time we have
undisputable evidence of excellent
governance
so i would say that yes
from all of this evidence put together
it is clear that we indians were the
first to develop
an excellent system of large-scale
governance governance on on a large
scale so yes i agree with the statement
that you've made
kosovo says what were the conditions
that gave rise to monotheism or
anti-polytheism in the ancient medieval
period
see if you look at the various cultures
all across the world
you see that all of these cultures all
of these ancient cultures were
polytheistic
if you look at the ancient indian vedic
culture it was polytheistic if you look
at the broader
if you look at the persian culture
zoroastrianism it was polytheistic
do not believe the fake claims spurious
claims that
zoroastrianism is a monotheistic
religion ahura mazda is the supreme
deity but there are lots of other
deities also
in zoroastrianism so zoroastrianism
which was an offshoot of hinduism was
polytheistic
in buddhism which is
again part of hinduism you have all
kinds of bodhisattvas and other
divinities
so the dharmic culture was polytheistic
the large-scale indo-european culture
which came into existence as a
consequence of westward migrations of
ancient indians
this was also
without
any dispute without any doubt a
polytheistic culture all across eurasia
if you look at
the hunnic culture which gave rise to
the turkic culture and the mongolian
culture the hudnik culture was
polytheistic they were they were
worshippers of the
angriest pantheon of gods
the sky father tangri the mother goddess
umay and various other gods and
goddesses ancient japan was polytheistic
the polynesian cultures are polytheistic
uh
if you look at the native american
cultures they were also all polytheistic
whether it's north america whether it's
south america if you look at african
cultures again polytheistic so the world
was polytheistic
overall
now
about two two and a half three thousand
years i'm not sure when um
somewhere in this time frame
a monotheistic
belief system emerged out of the sands
of west asia out of the sands of arabia
so you know when you have polytheistic
cultures essentially emerge out of lush
green climates
africa is lush green mostly
india was lush green lots of river
valleys so polytheistic culture eurasia
europe is also reasonably uh
well vegetated and so on so again
polytheism thrived there but in the
harsh unforgiving climate of
the arabian deserts
somehow a monotheistic culture
came out of that
which is the
it it all began with the ancient judaic
culture which is a monotheistic culture
it gave rise to christianity and later
on to the islamic faith as well so these
are the three religions of the book they
say the three peoples of the book
so it's essentially different
manifestations of the same
same core
culture which is monotheism
so the conditions that gave rise to
monotheism where the conditions that you
find in a desert region
harsh unforgiving climate and the need
for extreme discipline in order to
survive that gave rise to this sort of
culture
so so that's how it happened and then it
spread everywhere and you know how it
spreads so we don't need to go into that
okay
dominic says should isro's main focus be
reusable rockets is it doing enough to
develop it as soon as possible isro
hasn't even
started
developing reusable rockets
it's it's very disappointing
so if you look at
spacex they developed
reusable rockets
and they developed a host of
technologies advanced technologies
innovative technologies which have made
them the most profitable private
space company in the world they are more
profitable than i think even lockheed
martin and other countries
uh sorry other companies and
their cost per launch
if you if you look at the amount of
money it takes to launch one kilo of
payload into space their cost per kilo
is the lowest it is lower than israel
lower than everybody else because they
have developed reusable rockets now this
technology is something even we can
develop in india but
we're not doing it
now if you look at the number of rocket
launches
various uh
space organizations are doing
or the since 20 since 2020 the chinese
have launched more than 70 or 80 rockets
since 2020 spacex alone has launched
more than 60 rockets
since 2020 isro has launched four
rockets
four
it's it's it's it's incredible
that there is no focus on on taking
israel forward
and i don't blame the scientists the
scientists don't
get to decide the budget
the scientists don't have any power any
decision-making power they are just
doing what they are told to do
which is following orders
and in india's most powerful rocket the
gslv is actually a mid-sized or small
sized rocket
the
kind of payload it can take to low earth
orbit isn't isn't very massive it's
about i don't know how much two tons
five tenths i'm not sure look it up
it is dwarfed by the capabilities of
spacex and the various chinese long
march rockets or even the russian
rockets so isro is still a puny little
space organization yeah it is it is it
has a reasonable track record with the
pslv which is an even smaller rocket
and the gslv is still under development
it is still not very reliable because
the last launch failed unfortunately
so what it's not this fault of the
scientists isro is not doing well if you
want to develop a rocket and make it a
reliable rocket you have to undertake
lots and lots of launches and iron out
all the little problems that obviously
will be there in any technology or in
any uh machine
so the only way to do that is to have
lots and lots of launches but
unfortunately it looks like there is no
ambition
on the on the part of the leadership
whoever is
issuing orders to israel
and so we are seeing nothing happening
there is no new rocket being developed
uh
so yeah it's it's uh disappointing
there's no new more powerful rocket
being developed there is no focus on uh
developing
the
self-lending
reusable boosters technology reusable
rocket technology nothing of that
there's no innovation happening at all
the only
few launches that happen happens
sporadically
and i hear that there's going to be this
human space flight program it's already
delayed i don't know when
the tests will happen
so i don't know man it's really
languishing in in the doldrums right now
israel
and uh
some people would blame it on kovid well
kowai did not prevent the chinese for
from continuing to launch rockets or the
americans from doing so but somehow it
it completely stopped
whatever israel was doing so that's very
disappointing that's all i can say about
this
um
do planets need to maintain a certain
range of mass weight
to stay in their orbit around the sun on
earth we are burning through fossil
fuels and future space exploration will
guarantee
that we begin mining for resources from
from other planets possibly meteors you
mean asteroids
this would have an impact on the weight
of the planet
if yes what would be the effect of
shifting out of orbit even slightly in
terms of gravity temperature etcetera
etcetera etcetera etc system
sustainability of life on earth
okay the main question is do planets
need to maintain a certain mass
to stay in orbit around the sun no
absolutely not
you have even small pieces of of rock
that are in orbit around the sun
so if you study how the force of
gravitation work and over here we're
talking about the force the newtonian
way of looking at gravitation
is the inverse square law even a small
rock like this
will be in orbit around the sun
so uh so to answer in brief planets
don't need to maintain any range of mass
or weight or anything to stay in orbit
around the sun orbits are guaranteed as
long as certain conditions are met an
orbit is essentially you're falling but
you're falling in a certain direction
that makes you miss your target all the
time so that's an orbit
uh so yeah so you don't need to maintain
any mass
to stay in orbit
of course if the
amount of mass of a planet changes the
orbit will shift accordingly so if
you're talking about a certain specific
orbit yeah
it it all depends on a variety of
factors including the velocity the mass
and all that
um but you know what what you're asking
is that if we mine resources from our
planets will it change the mass of the
planet no it won't
there will be no significant change in
the mass of our planet because of mining
or because of space travel so i don't
see any such thing happening
so to answer your question in brief
the the orbit of the planet will not
change
the mass of the planet will not change
to any significant extent because of
mining or space exploration and
therefore we will remain in whatever
orbit we are in
most likely until the end of the
end of the solar system in its current
state
prakhar sharma says can you please talk
about strange matter
and the strange quark how is it formed
in a neutron star in a quark star can it
start a chain reaction of stable strange
matter throughout the universe
how different is this is a quark star
from a black hole what if a strange
matter quark star is actually a black
hole
okay
what is the strange quark so there are
six quarks
in nature
what are quarks
the quarks are the fundamental building
blocks of the
of the particles that we observe the
protons neutrons
the protons and neutrons essentially
right
so the so the quarks and whatever other
matter we can observe right
so there are six quarks up down top
bottom strange charm up down strange
charm top bottom six generations
also six six quarks are in existence now
the protons and neutrons are made up of
combinations of the up clock and the
down quark uh the other quarks are
heavier so um
so whatever
elementary particles we observe they are
made up of essentially the top the up
quark and the down quark only various
combinations and permutations of these
two quarks
strange quarks are hypothesized to form
inside
neutron stars so inside neutron star you
have incredible
amounts of pressures
a neutron star is essentially a few
kilometers in diameter but it can
contains the entire mass of an entire
star it's essentially an enormous atomic
nucleus so it is possible that within
a neutron star because of the enormous
pressures that you that you have so what
happens
is that quarks have this confinement
property
if you try to take two quarts or three
quarks apart then the amount of energy
that you have to put into doing that it
leads to the creation of new quarks and
you can never have a single naked quark
but inside a neutron star where there is
such incredible pressure
this pressure causes the quarks to
deconfine that's what believed
and then you have this quark matter
floating around so deconfined quarks
just a sea of corks free quarks inside
the neutron star and that's called
quark matter
and it is possible
that because of the
pressure and the forces that are
present inside this quark matter inside
a neutron star you may see the formation
of strange quarks which are in
matter
which is the stablest matter
in the universe
so this is all confined inside a neutron
star but what you have is that you have
neutron star collisions
very rare events in which two neutron
stars collide with each other
and when such a collision happens
bits and pieces of the neutron star are
ejected thrown out
and in such a case
you may have some of this quark matter
being thrown out into the universe
and these are called what are they
called strangelets small pieces of cork
matter
and it is possible that if this sort of
material
quark matter strange let's
they uh
they come in contact with a regular star
they may convert the entire star into
quark matter if they come into contact
with the planet the entire planet will
be converted into
something made of quark matter so it is
certainly possible
but it's never been observed so this is
all
theoretical theoretically it can
certainly
happen but it's never been
observed
so a quark star is essentially a quark
is
essentially a neutron star whose
interior is made of quark matter only
the
exterior external shell may be may be
may may be composed of ordinary matter
so that's what a quark star is it is not
a black hole a black hole is way more
compact
and a black hole
it's essentially something whose
matter density density is so high
that even light cannot escape from it it
has an even horizon so that's a black
hole
so a strange matter quark star cannot be
a black hole
okay shantanu says what if we had
economic liberalization a couple of
decades earlier instead of 1991 would it
be any different from today
than today
yes certainly india would have been a
very different place if economic
liberalization had been done in 1947
itself so from 1947 onwards we had the
uh
neherubian socialism that was imposed
upon india
and what it did was it it created this
phenomenon called the nehruvian rate of
growth so india's economy grew at about
one or two percent per year despite
india being a desperately poor country
when you have a desperately poor country
and you have the right economic policies
you should see 10 to 25 percent growth
year upon year at least for a few years
but what mr nehru did was he stifled the
growth in the country
he imposed the the
the
nairobi and socialism on india
and india's growth just stagnated he he
perpetuated poverty and mediocrity in
the country
and eventually by 1991 or 92 i think it
was 91 was it by the time india had
become essentially bankrupt
and that's why the government had to
turn
to the world bank or the imf i don't
know which one it was
we had to turn to these
western
monetary
institutions for help
and in return for that we had to open up
the economy so this was done under the
prime ministership of mr pv narasimha
rao
and then the entire country was
transformed very quickly
so before 91 india was a closed economy
india was kind of like north korea in
some ways everything was closed off
uh we had one tv channel in india
in which you could never get any news of
what's happening out of the country so
india was closed off and the economy was
totally dead there was no progress
happening
industries were all state regulated
private industries were essentially not
allowed to run unless
well
all that
so if this liberalization had been done
in 1947 india would have been a first
world country today i mean see where
japan was in 1947 japan was a destroyed
country it had been flattened
by the
events of world war ii and they twin
nuclear bombings by the americans japan
was destroyed
and they rebuilt their economy from
there and by the 1960s 1970s japan had
again become a first world country
look at what china was in 1945 in 1947
it was also a destroyed country
and see where it is today
right so if india had done the same
things in 1947 in 1950 india would have
been a first world country of first
world economy today
so imagine how much time we lost
thanks to the policies of the great sri
jawal nehru and the subsequent congress
regimes
so india would have been very different
today had those reforms been undertaken
in 1947
rama lakshmi says with all due respect
sir i know the pure passion of freedom
that was there in subhash and rabos but
if we consider a hypothetical situation
where he becomes the leader of india
wasn't he a leftist
and how do you think his ideology would
benefit india in terms of kick starting
to become a big power
so the option that we have
let's say we have two options
mr nero and mr gandhi that's option a
and mr bose which is option b now we
have already seen
what happened
under mr nehru with the gandhian
philosophy
see what happened to india i just spoke
about it
india's economy grew at one percent or
two percent
now let's say we have you say that mr
bose was a leftist i disagree with that
i completely disagree with that there is
no evidence he was a leftist but let's
say hypothetically he was leftist
and let's say he would have imposed
what you would
what you would expect leftist or marxist
countries to do
that sort of economic policy so let's
look at what the vietnamese have done
have you seen the change in vietnam's
economy after the vietnam war
vietnam is
close to becoming
a middle-income country today
it's a communist country
technically
look at the chinese they are also
technically a communist country look at
where they are today
right
so if you look at these
so-called leftist countries and leftist
policies they are resulting in
significant growth
of the economy
and law and order and all that
so if if mr bose was an authoritarian
person and if he had leftist views let's
say
let's let's agree let's hypothetically
agree to that
would india's economy had have grown at
one person or two percent the way it
it grew under mr nehru
definitely not
mr bose was certainly in favor of of
industrialization
mr nehru prevented india's
so i think that whatever mr bose was
like his economic policies would have
led to a significant and rapid growth in
the india's economy
and and uh
so i i don't understand
why
i mean i respect your point of view you
must have been listening to various
perspectives and trying to learn history
perfectly absolutely nothing wrong with
that i personally disagree with the
perspective that mr bose was a leftist
he may have had some left-leaning
uh
so certain perspectives that today would
be considered to be left leaning but the
thing is this in any country that is
that has been newly liberated from
foreign occupation you need a period of
time
where the economy is tightly controlled
and it is taken in a certain direction
uh
it is shepherded in a certain direction
look at how south korea was
south korea became
south korea after the korean war was
again a totally destroyed country
and then it was under a dictatorial
regime for about 20 years and see the
transformation which happened so mr bose
wanted that sort of thing for india he
wanted
essentially dictatorship one party rule
for about a period of about 20 years
i you know what it may not have been a
very bad thing for india
we
in today's world we we talk about
democracy democracy is the best thing
dictatorship is bad you know look at
look at singapore
they had mr lee kuan yew who was nothing
but a dictator
it was a one-party system and he was the
supreme authority nobody dared go
against him
it was a dictatorship but look at the
way he transformed singapore
he was a benevolent dictator
right
so here we have an example
of a guy
who had this iron fisted rule over
singapore
but he took singapore in the right
direction
look at what singapore is today
right
and singapore was again a destroyed
country when it became free it was a
third world
it was a pure third world country very
poor
it was in in the in the depths of
destitution that's what singapore was
and within 20 years this man transformed
the fortunes of the country
through dictatorship if there had been
democracy in singapore singapore would
still be a third world country
and today you are seeing the gradual
transformation of singapore towards the
democratic towards a certain form of
democracy so i see i don't see anything
wrong with mr swabash bose's ideas for
how india should have gone in what
direction india should have gone i think
we have already seen the alternative to
mr bowles which is mr mishnero
and his
policies which totally
uh stifled india's growth so i think mr
bose's plans for india had he won had he
succeeded would have actually
kick-started india's economy the way it
should actually have right
okay sindhu shetty says is buddhism one
of the reasons for the fall of the
mauryan empire
so what you see in the mauryan empire is
that you had
uh
the first great emperor chandragupta
maurya the founder of the mauryan
dynasty
who under the uh mentorship and guidance
of the great
strategist and realist vishnu
became the emperor of india
in about a period of 20 or so years he
can so he he
he consolidated his power his rule over
essentially the entire indian
subcontinent
and he uh
reclaimed the land of gandhara from the
greeks and
that's one of the
largest
empires india has ever seen
so that is the genesis the beginning of
the mauryan empire then you had his son
bindusar then you had ashok
so ashok also he may have been a
tyrannical king etc but he was a very
powerful king
and it is under ashok that we see the
graduate the transition
to buddhism
so ashok after them
um
it's not after the kalinga war it is
actually before the kalinga war that he
became
uh a practicing buddhist he began to
practice the tenets and practices of
buddhism what we what we call buddhism
today but it is under ashok that uh
buddhism
went from being a fringe
uh
from from being a french cult into a
mainstream uh
culture
so it is because of state support that
this happened under ashok
and then what we see is that after the
death of ashok
the subsequent kings of the mauryan
dynasty
were not good enough they were not
powerful enough
and they were essentially all
insignificant and the
power of the of the immoran empire
slowly declined
and within about 250 or 300 years we
find that the last mauryan king
is assassinated by his own
sinopathy by his own commander-in-chief
and the reason for that was that
india was crumbling the empire was
crumbling under the the leadership of
the mauryan emperors so pusha
assassinated the last murray emperor and
took over the reigns of the country
and he again consolidated the country
and made it powerful again which is the
which is the shunga empire the shong
dynasty so we see the beginning of the
decline
of the mauryan empire
with the death of emperor ashok and it
is during the time of ashok that
buddhism also becomes
essentially the the
the dominant
philosophy or or culture in india the
buddhist way of
way of thought
so you could say that this cannot be a
coincidence
there is clearly uh
the two things do co inside
so
you could say it's one of the causative
factors this this entire
emphasis on pacifism
could have caused the decline of the
modern empire but we also see other
empires that have been described as
buddhist empires that have done very
well for instance today's historians
they described the kushan empire as a
buddhist empire they described kanishka
the great as a buddhist king which is
buddhist emperor which is not actually
true but even if you agree with the
historians you will say that he was a
military expansionist emperor
he conquered
most of south uh most of central asia
from the caspian sea to the sea he also
conquered present-day xinjiang of
present-day china
so he created an enormous empire and if
he was a buddhist then buddhism
certainly did not cause him to be
pacifistic right
but i would disagree that kanishka was a
buddhist
he was an indian and he
if you see about if you see about five
percent of his coins
have depictions of the buddha or the
other coins of depictions of other gods
and goddesses
uh but when coming back to the more an
emperor that is the more in empire there
is clearly a coincidence
the two things do coincide
the uh introduction of buddhism as the
official de facto state culture religion
whatever you want to call it and the
decline of the mauryan empire so it
could
certainly have been a causative factor
in the fall or the decline
of the mauryan empire
animal says our ncert textbooks never
mention the bravery of our rajput
warriors
the books books mention akbar as great
but not maharana pratap why are they
hiding the reality of our history
right
so it's not only the rajputs that are
marginalized
and whitewashed out of history in ncid
textbooks i think even the marathas are
kind of
glossed over maybe a
paragraph or two the marathas defeated
the turks and uh
freed india from the foreign occupation
and established a vast empire that went
all the way north to
southern afghanistan
so the marathas are
a very very powerful and very
consequential empire and and yet they
are not
they are kind of whitewashed in the ncaa
textbooks you find almost no mention of
the gupta empire
come on gupta empire was
massive it was enormous
and it was a period of a great cultural
efflorescence in india
and you had
great emperors like kumar gupta like
chandragupta
the great defender of india
then you have people like lalith
who again conquered central asia
right who is not mentioned at all
and in city i don't know how much they
mentioned the cholas
i mean just one chula empire
just one chola emperor rajendra chola in
one lifetime conquered the entirety of
southeast asia all the way to the
philippines
right
so none of these great warriors great
kings emperors
are
mentioned are
you will not see ncrt doing justice to
any of them and the same goes for the
brave rajput warriors rajputs are today
you will see demonized
they are kind of ridiculed in in
contemporaneous dialogue
because of the perspectives and the kind
of image that the indian text books have
created of the rajputs which is
completely distorted the rajputs were
incredibly brave warriors nobody has
spilled
more blood than the rajputs in defending
india from the turks
and
that's not how they are portrayed so
that is that is just terrible it's
tragic and it needs
to change that's why i keep saying we
need to reform the education system and
we need to rewrite our history textbooks
we need to decontaminate the history
textbooks and make them purely 100
factual and nothing else
okay let's take one more question
prakash says say something about success
and failure
and why sometimes giving 100 doesn't
yield results
the results don't depend
solely on the amount of effort you put
into a certain endeavor they also depend
on the strategies you you pick
on the strategy you choose
right so if you choose the wrong
strategy then no matter how hard you
work
you're not going to get the results that
you desire
let's let's take the game of football
if you choose the wrong strategies
against the wrong team
you're going to lose no matter how hard
you work
right
if you if you go to let's say if you
let's say let's take the example of
cricket
you know that if you go to south africa
or australia the pitches are very hard
and bouncy and good for
baseballing fast bowling but if you go
there and use you use you pick five
spinners in your team you're gonna get
thrashed
even if the spinners work really really
hard
so if you choose the wrong tactics the
wrong strategies the wrong policies
you're going to fail no matter how hard
you work
the other thing is that
there is an inherent see in any sport
in any business
or in anything else in life there is an
inherent delay
between cause and effect
whether it is tennis whether it's
football whether it's cricket whether it
is a certain business it's a certain
industry
when you
do something new
you will not see results immediately
sometimes it will take a week to see the
results
some sometimes it will take a month
sometimes it will take three years
to see results it all depends and every
sport every business has a certain
characteristic inherent delay between
cause and effect and in sports
the best players that the greatest
champions
they understand this delay very well
so that's another aspect that you do
take into consideration that in anything
you try you cannot expect to see results
immediately
you try something and you do it for
three days and you get then you give up
because you get disheartened nothing
happened
that's not how that's not how it works
you have to study
the industry you're in or or the
business you're in
and you do or whatever else you're
trying to achieve
you understand that properly and you
understand that you will not see results
immediately so you have to understand
how long it will it typically takes
before you see results and things like
that
so that is what leads to success if you
can master all of these things properly
let me take one final question one more
wisdom bro says why does india have very
few cave paintings of the ice age
because we have not looked see first of
all india doesn't have a lot of caves
uh caves typically you will find where
you have uh
mountains and hills
and uh
so you have some cave paintings like the
bimbekta cave paintings and things like
that but i am not sure if our
archaeologists have discovered all the
caves that exist or not
so there are many uh
places where you have caves and those
have not been explored
so that could be one of the reasons
and the other thing is that india's
climate was always reasonably warm and
the ice age if you go down south towards
peninsular india
then you may not have had that much of
an effect at the ice age possibly
and therefore people may not have had to
live in caves
that's also a possibility so there are a
number of factors but most likely there
must be more cave paintings that are
still waiting to be discovered and our
archaeologists have done nothing because
they are busy looking at mughal
monuments and restoring them so that
could be one of the reasons
so
it needs to
be seen if you can find some more i'm
sure there are many more
all right my friends that brings us to
the end of today's session thank you
very much for all the very interesting
questions
and tomorrow we will have a video chat
session so those of you who want to have
face-to-face
uh who want to ask the whatever
questions you have face to face
i'll see you tomorrow be prepared with
your best questions one question per
person
so i will see you all tomorrow thank you
so much for the questions take care
and i will see you tomorrow bye
you